Register of the American Friends Service Committee. Civilian Public Service records
Hoover Institution Archives
American Friends Service Committee, Civilian Public Service records
1940-1946
XX228
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Bulletins, serial issues, reports, handbooks, correspondence, memoranda, and other printed materials relating to the American Friends Service Committee (AFSC) Civilian Public Service, an organization founded to provide alternatives for conscientious objectors to war and members of peace churches during World War II by establishing work camps to conduct duties of national importance.
American Friends Service Committee. Civilian Public Service.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1917 American Friends Service Committee founded to provide alternatives for conscientious objectors to war and members of peace churches.
1917-1918 AFSC provides relief during World War I.
1918 Committee begins working in Serbia, Russia, Poland, Germany, and Austria to provide relief following World War I.
1930-1945 Provides relief in Nazi Germany, Spain, and France.
1937-1943 Builds Penn-Craft community for unemployed coal miners in Fayette County, Pennsylvania.
1940 Congress passes an act creating Civilian Public Service (CPS) camps for conscientious objectors to fighting in World War II.
1941-1947 Civilians perform duties of national importance in CPS camps.
1947 Helps refugees in India and the Gaza Strip.
1950-1953 Provides relief during Korean War.
1954-1962 Provides relief during Algerian Civil War.
1955 Publication of the book Speak Truth to Power: A Quaker Search for an Alternative to Violence.
1956 Provides relief during Hungarian Revolution.
1960-present Works with civil rights and peace movements across the United States and internationally.
1966 Creates programs to help civilians in North and South Vietnam.
1967-1970 Provides relief during Nigerian Biafran War.
1970-present AFSC continues to provide peaceful alternatives to war and relief in war-torn countries.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of newsletters, reports, bulletins, correspondence, serial issues, and other printed matter relating to the American Friends Service Committee's Civilian Public Service branch, conscientious objectors to World War II, compulsory non-violent alternatives to serving in the war for members of established peace churches in the United States and aforementioned conscientious objectors to war.
Conscientious objectors--United States.; Pacifism.; Peace.; Service, Compulsory non-military--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscientious objectors.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--War work.
- General Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
- Printed Matter, 1940-1946
  - Administrative directives, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - American Friends Service Committee: Civilian Public Service Newsletter, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Articles, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Essays, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Executive Reports, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - General Letters, 1940-1946 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Handbooks, circa 1945 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1940-1946 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
  - Minutes, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Pamphlets, circa 1944 (Box-folder 2: 7-8)
  - Reports, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Serial issues published by AFSC, 1940-1946
    - #53, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - #59, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - #81, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - #84, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - #134, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Asferco News, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Calumet, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Camp Antelope, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Camp Coshocton, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Communique, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - The Compass, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 3: 11-12)
    - Cooperative Newsletter, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Cooperstown, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Days of Our Year, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - De Todo, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Education Secretaries Newsletter, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - Grass Roots, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - High Time, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Information, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 4: 3-5)
    - Journal of Unitology, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Just Among Ourselves, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Los Angeles Quaker, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - The Mono, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - New Roots, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - News Notes, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - The Open Ballot, 1943 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - The Patapso Peacemaker, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Personnel News, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - The Plowshare, 1941 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Pocomoke Opinion, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - The Powellsville News, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - The Rebel Clarion, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Rhythms, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Sage Opinion, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - San Dimas Rattler, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - The Souvenir, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - The Sphere, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - Stockley, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - This is Our Story, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Whispers, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 13-14)
    - Zalduondo Newsletter, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 5: 15-16)
  - Special Projects Bulletin, undated (Box-folder 5: 17)
- Subject File, 1943-1946
  - Bull Pen, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    Scope and Contents note
    Newsletters, bulletins, and other informational materials for workers who worked with livestock animals through the American Friends Committee Civilian Public Service organization.
  - School of Pacifist Living, 1943 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    Guidelines, curriculum, bulletins, and other informational materials on a school promoting non-violence based in Cascade Locks, Oregon.